here's the 30C lesson on what Legends
know never practice nunchucks in a
crowded room never eat choli before a
road
trip always take your shirt off before
you IR
it don't take a call near a swimming
pool and don't forget saving is not
investing Legends don't just say they
invest in mutual funds mutual fund
Investments are subject to Market risks
read old scheme related documents
carefully
how do we make the case that while grave
dangers are threatening to return the
old demons buried for a generation are
stirring it's time to call your troops
back to the barracks not send them
through the battlefield but call them
back to the bars we are talking about
Punjab and the six but hello you might
ask where is the war Punjab is quiet and
probably more peaceful and lawful than
any state in North India definitely more
than any state in the Hindi Heartland
the six just voted in large numbers in
state and loah elections dissing The
Almighty BJP their choice aadmi party is
even more of an outsider than the BJP or
the Congress where is the problem the
challenge what grave dangers are we
talking about what is stirring and where
is the War One challenge of being in
power or more importantly being in a
position of total power is that it makes
people believe that they must do
something with it inside every Power
System there is a latent da don kote it
you need you need that monstrous
malevolent windmill to Tilt at Sanu
Panza by your side so far so good except
it isn't megal sant's World from 1605 ad
and it gets more complicated now than
the windmill is located in British
Colombia Canada it is the troops
fighting those demons there that need to
be recalled to the barracks because the
land the people the politics that needs
attention is here a 5 and a half hour V
Bharat train ride or just an hour's
flight from New Delhi to Amritsar there
is no War battle or even Skirmish there
there is an unhappy Sullen and even
increasingly frust red population
wanting to leave India through
immigration which will be nearly
impossible now the statements the
separatists make the Abominable table
and displays at their parades the
slogans the posters and selfies with
assault rifles are not India's Problem
by the way I'm intrigued as to what
hardip Singh ner was conveying by posing
in a saffron Banana Republic t-shirt all
of these involved at the outer limit a
few thousand people if at all if they
are a nuisance it should bother their
host countries because they are armed
and have their own underworld with
deadly gang rivalries significantly none
of this happens in the US they are much
more careful with their immigration and
visas and their law enforcement is much
tougher this only happens in snowflakey
Canada G patwan Singh panu who sticks
the nastiest finger in India's eye from
the US is careful with his words he puts
his training as an attorney to good use
his Holdings will say destroy or Crush
India take a close look at the fine
print at the bottom and it'll be
footnoted with something like with
ballots not bullets in fact the nastiest
thing he which was seen as him saying
nobody should travel by Air India after
November 19 Mrs Gandhi's birth
anniversary last year and also the day
the cricket ICC Cricket World Cup was
beginning in India he was careful to say
however no sick should travel by Air
India because it'll be dangerous now he
could say implying thereby that six life
is is in danger in India he is very
clever too clever by half because he
does not want to run a foul of the law
in the US that's the difference between
the US and Canada it's certainly much
worse in Canada sort of in the middle in
Britain it it waxes and wains and
whatever happens in Australia New
Zealand Etc and in some other countries
relatively
marginal they can be infuriating
irritating infuriating but do they
matter or do they matter so much that we
take the fight to them at the risk of
strategic ties of existential
significance given the neighbors we have
or more specifically the neighbor we
have to the north namely China if wise
big power must have the ability to weit
friendships threats and the timing of
its actions it is also human that we
tend to respond first to whatever
irritates us the most at any point of
time yet the experience of Nations
societies even our own personal and
professional lives tells us that if we
merely take a deep breath let that
moment of anger pass we always wonder
the next morning is this what I was
going to war over or is this over which
I was breaking a relationship quitting
my job firing an
employee powerful people organizations
and definitely Nations do not let anger
determine their actions none of these
noisy separatists believe in some
equivalent of a Biblical inevitability
of a sovereign sick State and most can't
win a pchat election or collect a 100
armed people behind them in Punjab in
fact forget armed people most will
struggle to get a couple of thousand
unarmed people behind them in Punjab one
way of looking at them is as people who
were once fellow Indians who now are
mostly Canadians and are helping the
pakistanis and their isi spend whatever
remains of their money they are making a
living from it if the pakistanis think
they're getting value for their money
just because they can get India trolled
good luck to the Pakistani India and its
formidable intelligence assets can pay
the compliment back to the pakistanis in
Pakistan which they had been doing until
the careal in the anglosphere brought
about a hus India the us and even Canada
will see their respective stats play out
in the course of time if in different
ways both will follow different
trajectories ties between Sovereign
Nations especially ones that share so
much do not remain broken for too long
the US and India have already moved
forward compartmentalizing the panu
issue what will not change however is
the fact that large and influential
sections of the sik diaspora will
continue to live in both countries in
Canada they are electorally significant
in in a number of constituencies or what
is called as ridings there in both the
US and Canada they will continue to be
funded and fueled by the isi we are less
than a fortnight away from the 4th
anniversary of indraa Gandhi's
assassination and the massacres of six
that followed it also it also follows
that this is the 40th year of Operation
Blue Star it took a much bloodier decade
post raal then his three active years of
Insurgency for normaly to return to
Punjab there have since been three
decades of total peace in Punjab bying
the odd incident here and there some
some sacrilege some targeted killing but
at a very sporadic level there are
however stirrings of anger and
frustration it comes primarily from the
state's economic decline there is also a
rising belief that the SS have lost
their traditional ability to punch above
their weight in population terms in the
National Power structure it might look
odd that I say so weeks after another
sick has taken over as an armed forces
Chief if in this case but the power at
the center now resides fully with the
BJP the party the six like the least
check out the vote shares from the last
general elections and several elections
before that as well the BJP lacks a sick
leader from Punjab and the shiron AAL
cease to be an NDA Coalition partner in
2020 whatever whatever the bjp's
political logic sing ties with the
akalal did not serve the national
interest as atal bihari vajpai often
explained the challenge in Punjab was a
sik Hindus Schism the best answer was an
alliance of the primary sik and Hindu
parties the akalal and his BJP with that
broken everything is up in the air
theales are unpopular
and that's getting worse they getting
more unpopular and in the space they are
V vacating the religious space the
radicals are moving in it's also called
the Panik space in Punjab Panik from
kala P this vacuum in Panik politics is
is a danger and please save your virtue
signaling on secular politics Etc first
of all you say this in Punjab they will
tell you immediately that if the BJP
seeks a Hindu Nation how can you how can
how can you question some wanting a sick
nation that is said by the way only
rhetorically Amit pal Singh has been
subsumed for example by Democratic
politics and his incarceration has
caused no upheaval the tougher question
is who controls the sick faith and its
biggest temples their resources and
institutions we'll talk about this in
Greater detail that at some point but
today let me just see this week let me
just say that that is done by an elected
body the shirimani gurudwara prad
committee or sgpc for which only
observant six can vote that election was
last held in 2011 and one reason it is
delayed a fresh election is delayed is
the Haring of the number of eligible
sick voters in the ongoing enrollment we
spoke about these complexities in an
episode of kak letter of which I will
share a link with you the observant sick
numbers are declining for a number of
reasons as we detailed in several
National interest pieces there is the
fear of Christian conversion there is
the popularity of the dasas the
observant six numbers are declining for
a number of reasons as we detailed in in
a bunch of national interest pieces of
which I will share links with you with
the description however the big issues
are the popularity Rising popularity of
the dasas Christian conversions and also
many six not fully conforming to all the
requirements of the siik religious
Doctrine all of this adds up to
insecurity and worry add to this susp of
the BJP at the center there is no
Rebellion about the slogans and posters
of the kind you will see on these coming
40th anniversary so be prepared for that
will you lock them all up under uapa or
NSA if not by go to war with a few
hundreds doing the same thing two oceans
away that's why we need to call those
troops back with the bcks
[Music]
[Applause]